okay first I'd like you to follow follow
your breath
as focus on the exhale first and then on
the inhale
we'll take about 30 breaths
just relax relax your face very
important
especially your mouth and your eyelids
tighten your
abdomen slightly
especially the lower part
but not too tight
keep your hands soft
and push back your shoulders
stay very aware of the exhales
now on the exhale I'd like you to Exhale
from your right nostril
so that's the beginning of the breath
at the start of your breath you exhale
from the right nostril
and then the air circles around and
comes into your left nostril
nostril so I'd like you to take 30
breaths
exhaling from your right nostril
and inhaling from your left nostril
30 breaths if you're one of your
nostrils is blocked
just imagine that the breath is going
that way
if both of your nostrils are blocked you
can breathe through your mouth
but just imagine that the breath is
exhaling
from your right nostril
and coming into your left nostril
very long exhale
until the lower abdomen tightens on the
exhale so you might have to
almost exhale twice
push out a second
more conscious exhale from the right
nostril
personally I like to keep my dursty my
gaze
of my eyes
even though my eyes are closed
I like to keep the Gaze
up at the Horizon so my eyes are looking
slightly over the horizon
uh even though my eyelids are closed and
then that keeps your
head from nodding down when you're
watching your breath
thank you
now I'd like you to think of one
interaction you had yesterday or this
morning
with another person
when did you meet someone when did you
talk to someone yesterday
or if you didn't meet anyone yesterday
and the day before
one interaction you had
with another person
then I'd like you to recall
why did you need them what what were you
leading them for why did you meet the
other person
what were you hoping
to achieve maybe it was just a few
minutes talk
or catch up with them or
why why did you
interact with another person
by the way it could be online also or on
your phone
and then I'd like you to think about why
did they meet with you what were they
trying to get out of interacting with
you
when they spoke to you
there must be some need
or some something they want
out of talking to me
what was it that they wanted
what was their hope
for that interaction
and lastly
how did they see you if if you put
yourself
in their body
and remember that interaction you had
how do you think you look to them
I I don't mean your appearance
necessarily I mean the way you were
acting
and the way you were speaking
the feeling that God about how you are
thinking about them
if you go from the mountain of your body
and cross over to the mountain of their
body
and look back at your Mountain
how do you look to them
how how
kind were you how thoughtful were you in
the interaction how did the
how did you feel to them
actually pretend you're looking at you
yesterday
from their eyes
and then please come back to your breath
again exhales from the right nostril
and inhales through the left nostril
even if it's only imaginary
Gaze on the horizon even though your
eyes are closed
then please open your eyes
take a stretch
drink something
especially if you're a diamond mountain
drinking okay
you guys were supposed to meditate
yesterday about
uh people who are your bosses and people
who are your colleagues and people who
are your employees or report to you
uh
would anybody like to share how it felt
or any observations
yeah
oh and I specifically
what emotion did you feel in the three
cases okay did was there a
was there a pattern where you tend to
feel the same emotion for your boss
and then you tend to feel the same
a typical emotion for somebody who works
for you
yeah okay
um I love this one this is amazing
um
just because I felt like the
applications to this particular practice
like not just personally but
professionally to start so
remarkable and I thought about this all
night how like when we're a team we're
attempting to have like a common goal
and so oftentimes in like leadership for
example you're trying to get your team
on board and so for me to put myself in
like my colleagues shoes
what oh sorry
uh my colleague's shoes
um it allowed me to sort of
look at like for example
um my my colleagues are beginning to
change and so how can I help
them I guess you know when they were
looking at I guess me
I'm that's hard to explain I guess but
I'm in my colleague's shoes looking at
me yeah and so it made me shift
how I could help them I guess you know
and it put me into a more of a state of
service like mentally like how can I
take away something off of their plate
in order to sort of have the bigger
picture of being successful and so in
each case I found myself
um
kind of looking at like
as a person how can I look at me
so confusing
um
like for example at this like when I did
the boss last night
um
the the difference or the the flavor
between the colleague and the boss were
slightly different in the colleagues
sense I was how can I take a little bit
off of their plate
and then in the boss's sense the feeling
was more like
how can I help similar how can I act a
little bit
um better in order
I don't know it was almost like um
just relax a little bit you know like I
found myself trying to sort of like how
do I
and not not trying so hard with the boss
I guess was the harder one because um
I found myself trying to like relax a
little bit in order to serve them
really is what it came down to
and then in the the lower one for
example
um
how can I sort of help them how can I
see the world
from their point of view and maybe make
them relax a little bit
so it was really beautiful I just
enjoyed it a lot
somebody else
the way uh when you're translating
Shanti Deva this section
it's extremely difficult
and what I ended up doing was me
as the boss me as me me as the employee
so you have to use as
to make clear which me you're talking
about
it gets confusing so in the translation
and by the way I think Shanti David does
it on purpose
because it gets very confusing who's me
and so it's helpful in your own mind to
say me as the boss looking at me as me
you know how does that feel and
so I just that's a
that's something you might want to try
when you're meditating on it or when
you're describing it to your friends
okay
I have done this every time you breathe
pause
I have done this meditation
like 40
so I had some experience with it
and the first thing I've realized is
that a lot has changed since the first
time that I've done this meditations and
now
um one of my conclusions in the past was
that Envy feels like hatred when you are
on the other side
and the SE meditation uh yesterday
um it was about for me it was about
jealousy at the same level with the
colleagues
and when I changed myself with the other
person I felt like I'm surrounded by
thieves
so jealousy is being felt like you are
surrounded by thieves
that by thieves that want to grab what
you have oh wow okay yeah
okay so the emotion was
jealousy yeah this is my I'm interested
in the emotion yeah anybody else
don't be shy
yeah
this is a fantastic meditation
you know as we're learning
to love everyone equally
gosh what a
wonderful perspective
to be looking at myself through their
heart
and checking in with how they're feeling
standing in front of me exchanging with
me
so it opens my eyes
and I felt
I I want to
stay in that state all day
just so I can
help them feel safe
in my presence
and supported
and
filling their needs
you know based on what I'm looking at
right now as I look at me
at me and
I don't know I think it's a very
profound meditation and thank you for
sharing this with us
thank you
and then after this
can you hear me okay
a little louder okay thank you again
Michael for giving us this
meditation I also have done it before
this time I was focusing on a colleague
and jealousy
this colleague has shared with me that
she's felt jealous before of me
and I hadn't thought too much about that
when I put myself in her shoes
me as my colleague
and looked back at me as me
I saw an arrogant person
and it was pretty uncomfortable
so I get the chance to look at jealousy
and pride together which is up for me so
thank you yeah nice
watching the
thank you for these wonderful teachings
I unfortunately have a question uh
which is that I was doing my boss and
I'm in a very strange situation at the
moment in my job where everybody
thinks my boss is unqualified for his
position and it looks like he they might
let him go soon it's to that extent I'm
the only person
who treats him well and he believes that
I think he's qualified
and so when I put myself in his shoes
looking back at me it was almost this
like and You Brutus like you also think
I'm unqualified but then when I put
myself in my shoes again then I'm like
then how am I supposed to am I supposed
to change
what I think of like I'm nice to
but I kind of also don't think so should
I think he's qualified when I kind of
don't think he's qualified
well you're not talking about me right
okay
um
I'll give her a short answer uh you know
I I spent 19 years in a corporation in
uh in Manhattan and a large company and
uh I I know the politics
you know and I know the interactions and
um
I think what what happened with me was
I started to realize
in I started to think about what they
call it group delusion
a group hallucination
so there's this feeling when you're in a
group
that if if everyone agrees with you
that the boss is incompetent
than the boss is incompetent and if you
know what I mean so if you can just get
someone else to agree with you
that someone is a problem then they're
really a problem
you know so the more people who vote for
you
uh and your opinion then the more true
it is
that your opinion is true but then if
you're
a Buddhist logician
I mean technically everyone can be wrong
and uh just because more people
support a Viewpoint in a group
doesn't mean it's correct
so I think you have to be there's a
tendency
to try to walk around the company and
get support for your opinion of somebody
and if you can get two or three friends
to say yeah that person's really an
you know and then you feel like
Yeah I'm then I'm I'm right you know and
they're wrong so I think that's one
tendency but I think your question is
different if I put myself in your shoes
uh what you're really asking is if if
you really do believe they're
incompetent and but they you're kind of
like the last person
that they're hanging on to to to get
support from
what's the Buddhist thing to do
and uh
I think it's that
um
put yourself in their
shoes and
do your best to find a solution
okay so I'd like everyone if you don't
take anything else home
from this week
take home the idea
means a third third option
okay there's what they want
that's what you want and then I I would
like you to get used to thinking of
third options and and again that's I
think
uh the essence of innovation innovation
in a company or or in a project in a in
a non-profit organization
I think Innovation is is mainly with
people
okay to innovate a process like we I
innovated X-rays of diamonds
you can detect a fake diamond out of a
hundred thousand diamonds with x-rays
and no one ever used it before for that
and so that's a technical uh Innovation
uh but I think most Innovations uh are
between people are in your interactions
with other people so I encourage you to
think of a punk Zumba so Pung Zumba
means
uh do I pretend to support them
and do I pretend to
do I pretend to espouse the opinion that
they are not incompetent
uh or do I express my real opinion and
then what you've done is you've set
yourself up for a dichotomy or two
choices yes or no
and I think a great leader and a great
employee
a great follower has to learn to
you have to find a a solution which
makes both people happy
and and that's the Great result of
practicing Tong LAN
and dogs over a long period of time
is
is the realization
that a solution has to serve both people
and it's similar to the principle in in
negotiation in a business negotiation
uh
the perfect negotiation
ends with both people getting more than
they thought they wanted
uh and and interactions
with other people
should result in both parties getting
more happiness than they expected
so how you do that with your boss
uh uh that's up to you by the way uh
it's not
Buddhism
uh
to never fire somebody
okay I fired
a lot of people the first one was hard
the second one was less hard
uh but uh we used to clean out the
company every December
because Christmas is 60 of the diamond
business
so you you were you build up the
workforce you you add about an extra
half fifty percent extra people and then
you
then you have a purge in January because
there's no nobody buys diamond rings in
January
after Christmas nobody
so then you just clean out the company
and if you don't
the company fails and nobody gets
everybody's family suffers
so I'm not saying it's not a Buddhist
thing
to lose money and ruin a company if
there's someone who's acting up
or somebody's a problem or a boss is
incompetent
then uh it's not a Buddhist thing to
keep an incompetent bosses hurting
everybody you know that that's not a
Buddhist practice
but a Buddhist practice would be to find
them
a job that's even more interesting for
uh where they serve other people happily
you see I mean like that
so that would be a Buddhist practice
okay